RG 003, New London County, County Court Files
Connecticut State Library
The first Baptist case dates to 1704 when a complaint was filed against Benjamin Stark of Groton "for his Entertaining A Ministry or Church Administration in his house."83 These meetings led to the formation of the first Baptist church in Connecticut and to additional cases involving this group of dissenters, including those involving the settlement of Valentine Whitman, the first pastor.84 After passage of legislation in October 1729 that reluctantly granted toleration to Baptists, the typical Baptist case concerned efforts of individuals to secure release from taxation to support the established Church.85 The first such case took place at the June 1731 court meeting, John Congdon v. Joshua Raymond and John Noble. Congdon stated that he was a Baptist who attended worship in Stephen Gorton's New London church and argued that he should be excused from taxes supporting the Congregational Church. The defendants seized two cows worth £20 to pay these taxes, but the defendants collected court costs on a legal technicality."86 The 1752 memorial of Thomas Wait of Lyme represents a more typical example. He asked to be released from paying taxes to support the Congregational Church in the First Society. He stated that he was a Baptist under the pastoral care of Elder Joshua Rogers and included a document by members of the congregation who attested that Wait belonged to that church. Despite a deposition from Stephen Gorton, claiming that Rogers was not in communion with any recognized Baptist church, the court granted the memorial.87 The last two Baptist cases date from the 1840s at a time when the denomination had achieved respectability. In the first lawsuit, the Central Baptist Society of Norwich sued "The Mechanics and Manufacturers Library Association" for rental of property owned by the church and, in the second, State v. Samuel D. Tilden of East Lyme, the defendant was charged with disturbing public worship.88
Files contain several cases in which Separatists were fined for abusing ministers of the Gospel or charged with profane speech, as when Mary Williams was accused in 1748 of vile and profane discourse for saying, "I am Jesus Christ and you are the Divel, git behind me Satan."89 Earlier, in June 1742, however, thirty-two Separatist men and women from the First Society in New London petitioned the court for permission to be classified as sober dissenters and thereby released from paying taxes to support the established church. The petition was continued until November, at which time the court granted twenty-eight males the right to "Soberly and Conscientiously Dissent from the Way of Worship and Ministry Established by the Laws of this Colony," the first such privilege granted to Separatists in the colony.89 Separatists, like Baptists, claimed the right to be released from paying taxes to support the established church. In one such instance in 1791, John Lord unsuccessfully sued the Society Committee of the Third Church in Lyme for £30 damages because he was taxed by the society despite having attended Elder Daniel Miner's church for more than a decade.91 A year later the State charged transient Hezekiah Goddard with "tumultuous and offensive Carriage" for threatening the Reverend Paul Park of Preston and calling him "an old knave and A lying villain."92
Only a handful of cases concern the tiny Anglican minority in New London County and most concern efforts by missionaries from the Society for the Propagation of the Gospel in Connecticut to collect parish rates from Anglican Church members, usually without success. In a case that involved two dissenting groups, Ebenezer Punderson v. Daniel Fisk, the plaintiff, Anglican missionary for the SPG, sued Baptist minister Fisk for violating the Connecticut statute against unlawful marriage by marrying his daughter Hannah to Solomon Avery of Preston.93 In a post-Revolutionary War case, Ebenezer Punderson and Henry Billings, members of the "Established Church of England" and imprisoned for debt petitioned the court to extend the bounds of the Norwich prison yard to include the meetinghouse of the Church of England. The court took no action on the petition.94
An important Shaker defamation and slander case was tried in 1785. Keren Eggleston, 2d of Stonington sued Reuben Rathbun, "who the Shakers Call a Prophet," for £800 damages after the defendant had accused the plaintiff of "whoredom & Bestiality." The court received nine depositions that testified to the truth of the charges. The court found Rathbun guilty and assessed him £20 damages and costs.95
Most Congregational cases involved efforts by ministers to secure funds, salaries, or property stipulated by contract with the church society but not paid to the minister. In one typical case, Matthew Griswold, King's Attorney, sued John Clark, Samuel Bushnell, and Phillip Kirtland, Committee for the Second Society in Saybrook for payment of £360 due for the 1751 salary of the Reverend Abraham Nott.96723. In a second example, the Society Committee for the 2nd Church in Preston sued John Green, Jr. in 1783 for £15 stating that he had subscribed £8 in 1773 "for the Support and Maintenance of A Regular Orthodox Minister" but had failed to pay the agreed sum. The plaintiffs recovered £12-15-2 damages and court costs of almost £3.97
Perhaps the most interesting class of cases consists of lawsuits for defamation and slander. The records contain almost 150 of such cases for the period before the American Revolution and more than 200 thereafter. Although the plaintiff is suing for large monetary damages on the charge of defamation, the person is being slandered for one or more of several reasons. The major subjects include the following: perjury or swearing a false oath (28 cases), theft (26), counterfeiting or forgery (12), bankruptcy or unable to pay bills (12), lascivious carriage (11), drunkenness (9), adultery (9), prostitution (6), and attempted murder (4).98 In one June 1757 case, Thomas Clark and his wife Rebecca of Lyme sued Nathan Jewett. The plaintiff had kept a house of public entertainment for several year but was not re-nominated by the civil authority in Lyme after Jewett slandered the plaintiffs by asserting that Clark "Doth not Rule his Wife" due to the fact that Rebecca was a scold, "a Quarrelsome & Contentious Woman." The defendant was acquitted. In another case in November 1770, Samuel Baker v. Joseph Billings, Baker sued for £500 damages because Billings had falsely accused his wife Margaret of having carnal knowledge with a Negro man called Jack. At that same court session, Peter Bowdish v. Isaac Baldwin, the plaintiff sued for £500 damages on the false accusation that he was guilty of the "Capital Crime of Buggery" with a dog. The jury awarded the plaintiff £4 damages and the defendant appealed.
Table 2. Defamation and Slander, 1781-1855
1781-1789 10 4 8 3 0 5 30
1790-1799 10 2 4 2 1 3 22
1800-1809 11 6 6 3 0 7 33
1810-1819 16 6 3 1 3 7 36
1820-1829 11 9 5 3 3 5 36
1830-1839 4 5 4 1 1 5 20
1840-1849 5 7 2 0 0 5 19
1850-1855 1 7 0 0 0 5 13
Totals 68 46 32 13 8 42 209
Noteworthy lawsuits include one filed by Isaac Weeden of New London in June 1805 against Benjamin Brown demanding $500. The plaintiff stated that he was a merchant and trader whose business depended on having capital and offering credit. The defendant had slandered Weeden by claiming that, "Isaac Weeden has bought an Elegant Horse, Collected his Saddlebags full of Money, & run away with it & left his Family to Cheat his Creditors."102 In an 1811 case that was not prosecuted, Polly Smith accused Abigail Smith of "adultery, fornication, lewdness, whoredom or incontinency" with one John Ayer.103 The February 1850 court heard to case of Benajah Cook v. Oliver L. Wheeler. Cook sued for $500 damages because the defendant hanged an effigy of the plaintiff on a tree near a highway with a label saying, "B. Cook Justice has over taken the Pope."104 Finally in the last defamation and slander case brought before the court, Elder Reuben Palmer of Montville sued Joshua Rogers on the slander of "wilfully and maliciously removing or altering... boundaries of land."105
The other categories in which at least five lawsuits were filed consist of drunkenness (7), murder or attempted murder (5), fraud (5), and medical quackery (5). Unlike State prosecutions (Table 3), defamation and slander lawsuits did not increase with population, although the subjects of lawsuits changed somewhat from the pre-Revolutionary time period. Compared to the earlier period, theft and accusations of sexual misconduct cases increased and forgery/counterfeiting lawsuits decreased. The problem of definition is a recurrent one, as charges often covered a wide range of transgressions, like the February 1796 lawsuit in which Keziah Whipple was accused by John King of being "a damned Liar," "a damned Faggot," and "a damned Strumpet."106
The vast majority of cases adjudicated before the County Court consisted of civil cases, but criminal prosecutions on behalf of the King to 1776, Governor and Company of the State of Connecticut to 1784, and the State of Connecticut thereafter became increasingly important during the first half of the nineteenth century. Although many cases were withdrawn before being heard by the county court for a variety of reasons, including insufficient evidence, the failure of witnesses to appear, or successful prosecution by another court, the numbers are significant.
The typical State prosecution began with a complaint by a grand juror to a local justice of the peace.107 The person complained against was arrested and brought before the j.p. and the justice either made his own determination of guilt or innocence or bound the defendant over to the county court for later trial. The State's Attorney decided whether or not to try the case. In one representative example from November 1847, grand juror Leonard Hempstead of New London issued a complaint to John Grace, Esq. against Walter Edwards, "not being a taverner, with force and arms did sell... wine and spirituous liquor, to wit, one glass each of Rum, gin, brandy and wine to Joseph Ward." Constable Joseph S. Fitch arrested Ward, he was brought before j.p. Grace, and was bound over to the county court. State's Attorney John T. Wait declined to prosecute.108
The following table provides an overview of State criminal prosecutions for the period between 1781 and 1855.
Table 3. State Prosecutions, 1781-1855
1781-1789 11 12 84 9 4 58 178
1790-1799 8 7 13 7 4 8 47
1800-1809 17 16 7 9 0 3 52
1810-1819 30 34 14 11 4 19 112
1820-1829 66 57 4 39 1 5 172
1830-1839 132 146 29 36 16 42 401
1840-1849 251 157 147 35 83 78 751
1850-1855 120 132 131 36 52 50 521
Totals 635 561 429 182 164 263 2,234
As the table indicates, the number of State prosecutions of criminal offenses increased drastically, particularly for the period after 1830. The average number jumped from 17.2 per year in the decade of the 1820s, to over 40 for the next decade, 75.2 for the 1840s, and 83.7 during the 1850s. The rates of criminal prosecutions increased much more rapidly than population, although they reflected two 19th century trends - increased urbanization and the spread of poverty, particularly among minorities. Some 28.3% of the total number of indictments were for assault, followed by 25.1% for theft, and 19.2% for offenses associated with the misuse of alcoholic beverages. Three classes of offenses, then, constituted 72.6% of all State prosecutions and, if one adds the totals for tumultuous carriage (8.2%) and a variety of sexual crimes (7.4), then more than 88% of all presentments are accounted for.
The Other category includes presentments for malicious mischief (57), arson (33), election fraud (29), illegal intercourse with the enemy (23), nonpayment of excise taxes (21), counterfeiting (20), forgery (12), gambling (11), fraud (9), and escape from jail (9).
The documentation on prosecutions for assault, for example, provides information on the nature of each crime, the weapon or weapons used, the location where the offense was committed, the extent of injuries suffered, and the punishments inflicted upon conviction. In February 1787, for example, the State prosecuted Rebecca Morgan of Groton for beating and abusing indented servant Betty Freeman. The court found the facts of the indictment true, set Betty at liberty, and ordered the defendant to pay court costs.109
A close study of criminal assaults can also provide data on both perpetrators and victims, e.g. male on male, male on female, female on female, and female on male, not to mention adult on child and those of different races. People of color were much more likely to be victimized by whites than the reverse. In addition, the presentment tells the relationship, if any, between the criminal defendant and the victim. The February 1841 session, for example, contains six presentments for assault; three by white males on white males, two for husbands against wives, and one for a black man on a white man. The number of presentments is so large that researchers can break down the data by sex, age, and residence, thus crimes by and against women, by and against minors, and by and against transients can all be analyzed.110 The increasing number of crimes committed in urban New London and Norwich in the middle of the nineteenth century is also apparent. One can also examine to what extent crime may be associated with class, ethnicity, and race, as the appearance exists that African Americans and Irish were brought before the bar at much higher rates than their numbers would warrant.
The number of prosecutions for theft is equally impressive. The documents provide information on the perpetrator and victim, precise identification of the goods stolen, and the disposition of each case, including prison sentence and costs. In November 1834, the State prosecuted George Brown, a transient from New York, for theft from the store of Peleg Denison, Jr. of Waterford; John Brown and others from Norwich for stealing clothes from Taylor Thornton; Julia Ann Freeman, a woman of color, for several thefts in Norwich; transient George Potter and others in a theft of clothes from the store of John W. Fanning on Griswold; Joseph Saunders for theft of a silver watch from Juliet Forsyth; Charles W. Smith for purloining bank notes from Richard Lee; and transients Alexander Webster and George Smith for theft of clothing from the store of the Sheffield brothers in Stonington.111
The third classification of crime that led to a large number of prosecutions revolved around the sale of alcoholic beverages. The category of Strong Drink consists primarily of illegal sales of spirituous liquors by those unlicensed to do so, but it also includes prosecutions of persons chosen to be tavern keepers who failed to secure bond, sale of alcohol to habitual drunkards, and a small number of presentments against the intoxicated. Prosecutions for illegal sale of alcoholic beverages tended to cluster, for example, ten of fourteen cases for the 1810 to 1819 time period occurred in June 1817. Eight of the ten persons charged lived in New London and, indicative of most presentments for sale of strong drink without license, the State's Attorney declined to prosecute. The bulk of the prosecutions, 278 of 429, took place in the fifteen year time period from 1841 to 1855, perhaps reflecting the growth of the temperance movement and the influx of Irish immigrants to eastern Connecticut during the 1840s. The State's Attorney brought twenty-six indictments for illegal sale of liquor to the November 1847 court. He declined to prosecute in about two thirds of the cases, including one for the illegal sale of liquor to "an intemperate person." Eight cases were brought to trial, resulting in six verdicts of guilty and two of not guilty.112 Indictments of persons appointed as taverners by the court who failed to secure good behavior bonds date primarily from the 1780s.
The fourth most significant category of State prosecutions consisted of those for a variety of threatening and violent actions, e.g. threatening and abusing, tumultuous carriage, riot, and threatening to murder. In June 1824, the State unsuccessfully prosecuted Joseph Bolles and five others for riot, declined to prosecute Stephen Green for threatening to murder Stephen Chappell, convicted transient Henry Wright for threatening and stealing clothes from Saxton Miner, and charged four women and one man with threatening to maim or kill Eunice Avery. All five failed to appear at court and forfeited their bonds.113
The sexual crimes category consists of indictments for abortion, adultery, bigamy, fornication, incest, lascivious carriage, prostitution, and rape. The approximate number for each crime is: adultery (66), prostitution (32), keeping a bawdry house (24), fornication (19), rape or attempted rape (14), bigamy (4), lascivious carriage (3), abortion (1), and incest (1).114 Many of these are included in the table for Crimes Against Women, but as a general rule not those prosecuted for adultery, bigamy, and keeping a house of ill-fame, crimes for which males were often indicted. The courts prosecuted both males and females for adultery. In June 1840, for example, the State's Attorney prosecuted Mary Miller of Colchester, wife of Pomp Miller, for adultery with James S. Freeman and Freeman for adultery with Mary Miller. Both pleaded not guilty and judged not guilty.115 Fifty-two of fifty-seven persons indicted for keeping or maintain a bawdry house or residing in a "house of ill fame" occurred between the years 1845 and 1854 and more than half of the people prosecuted lived in New London. In February 1848, State's Attorney John T. Wait prosecuted five people of color from New London, Frank Sansom for maintaining a house of "ill fame" and four women for prostitution. The court found all guilty.116
Fornication, rape, or attempted rape forms the other two categories with significant numbers. By mid-century, most State prosecutions for fornication involved an underage female, as the prosecution of Alonzo Frisby of Groton for committing the crime with eighteen year-old Caroline Ashby. Although he pleaded not guilty, the court convicted him and sentenced him to three months in the county jail, a $50 fine, and payment of court costs.117 In a case of rape, George Godfrey of Norwich was accused of sexual assault on Julia Ann Crocker, a child of eight.118 The court also heard one case of abortion and one of incest, prosecutions so unusual that they deserve mention. The State charged Morgan Mott of Bozrah with attempting with "large quantities, to wit four ounces of a noxious and destructive substance called savin & a large quantity of the oil of taney & other deadly drugs with intent thereby to cause and procure the miscarriage of said Clarissa Hancox" of Colchester. The defendant was released after paying court costs.119 In the case of incest, Charles Miner of Lyme was accused of a "brutal and indecent assault... feloniously to ravish and carnally know" on his thirteen year-old daughter Lucretia. He pled guilty and was sentenced to six months in jail.120
The malicious mischief category consists primarily of crimes against property or livestock, such as two June 1820 indictments for chopping holes in the Shetucket River between Norwich and Preston thereby preventing people from passing and endangering their property and obstructing traffic along a public highway in Norwich by putting rails across it or the June 1838 prosecution of David Carrier of Colchester for entering the property of Epaphroditus Carrier, firing a loaded gun at an ox and injuring the animal.121 The election fraud cases are comprised primarily of prosecutions of non-voters for attempting to vote in town meetings or trying to vote twice, but the compiler also included the indictment of Samuel Burrows of Groton who accused the governor of bribery.122 The remaining cases, numbering 39, include presentments against towns for failing to maintain public highways (6), illegal smallpox inoculations (5), violations of laws regulating fisheries (3), publishing obscene materials (3), and one or two cases concerning such subjects as kidnapping, profane swearing, sale of infected meat, and the illegal performing of tricks of uncommon dexterity for profit.
The court records also allow researchers to find more information on important events in Connecticut history and to test conclusions made by historians who may not have examined court records. The Spanish Ship Case concerned a Spanish snow carrying gold, silver, and indigo that was intentionally wrecked by New London pilots in November 1752. The cargo was brought ashore, some of it was stolen, and Governor Roger Wolcott was defeated for re-election due to rumors that he had conspired to steal the cargo. Only one study has been published on the subject and no evidence exists that the author consulted New London County Court records.123 Files contain records on thirty-three cases between November 1753 and June 1755 on this subject.
In May 1763, the General Assembly passed "An Act for Relief of Insolvent Debtors who are willing to make Discovery of and deliver upon Oath their Estates for their Creditors' Benefit, and to release such Debtors from Imprisonment," due to the economic difficulties the colony encountered after the French and Indian War.124 Standard sources on the pre-Revolutionary era discuss the seriousness of these debt problems, but do not base their conclusions on a study of court records.125 The records from New London indicate that 14 insolvent debtors were involved in 36 cases between November 1763 and June 1774. Half of the insolvent debtors lived in Stonington and just three people, John Rathbun of Stonington, Abner Lee of Lyme, and Matthew Stewart of New London were concerned with 18 of 36 cases. Rathbun alone was the debtor in 10 cases. The evidence from New London County indicates that further study on insolvent debtors is needed and that previous conclusions may need to be modified.